-Yes, sweetheart?
-There's a girl wants to see you.
Her name's Wonderly.
-Customer?
-I guess so.
You'll want to see her, anyway.
She's a knockout.
Shoo her in, Effie, darling. Shoo her in.
EFFIE:
Will you come in, Miss Wonderly?
Thank you.
-Won't you sit down, Miss Wonderly?
-Thank you.
I inquired at the hotel for the name
of a private detective.
They mentioned yours.
Suppose you tell me about it
from the very beginning.
-I'm from New York.
-Uh-huh.
I'm trying to find my sister.
I have reason to believe that she's here...
...with a man by the name of Thursby.
Floyd Thursby.
I don't know where she met him.
We've never been as close
as sisters ought to be.
If we had, perhaps Corinne would have
told me
she was planning on running away.
Mother and Father are in Honolulu.
I've got to find her before they get back.
-They're coming home the first.
-You've had word of your sister?
A letter from her about two weeks ago.
It said nothing
except that she was all right.
I sent her a telegram,
begging her to come home.
I sent it to General Delivery.
That was the address she gave.
I waited a week and no answer came,
so I decided to come out here myself.
I wrote her that I was coming.
I shouldn't have done that, should I?
It's not always easy to know what to do.
You haven't found her?
No. I told her in my letter that I'd be at
the St. Mark and for her to meet me there.
I waited three whole days. She didn't come,
didn't even send a message.
It was horrible, waiting.
I sent her another letter.
Yesterday afternoon,
I went to the post office.
Corinne didn't call for her mail,
but Floyd Thursby did.
He wouldn't tell me where Corinne was.
He said she didn't want to see me.
I can't believe that.
He promised to bring her to the hotel,
if she'd come.
He said he knew she wouldn't. He promised
to come himself if she didn't. He--
Oh, excuse me.
Oh, it's all right, Miles. Come in.
Miss Wonderly, my partner, Miles Archer.
Miss Wonderly's sister ran away...
...with a fellow named Floyd Thursby.
They're here in San Francisco.
Miss Wonderly has seen Thursby,
has a date to meet him.
Maybe he'll bring the sister with him.
Chances are he won't.
Miss Wonderly wants us to find the sister,
get her away from him and back home.
-Right?
-Yes.
Now, it's simply a matter of having a man
at the hotel this evening...
...to shadow him when he leads us
to your sister.
If, after we've found her,
she still doesn't want to leave him....
-Well, we have ways of managing that.
-Yeah.
But you must be careful.
I'm deathly afraid of him,
of what he might do.
She's so young. His bringing her here is
a serious--
Mightn't he do something to her?
Leave that to us.
We'll know how to handle him.
But I want you to know
he's a dangerous man.
I honestly don't think
he'd stop at anything.
I don't think he'd hesitate to kill Corinne
if he thought it would save him.
Could he cover up by marrying her?
He has a wife and three children
in England.
They usually do, though not always
in England. What's he look like?
He has dark hair
and thick, bushy eyebrows.
He talks in a loud, blustery manner.
He gives the impression of being violent.
He was wearing a light gray suit and
a gray hat when I saw him this morning.
-What does he do for a living?
-I haven't the faintest idea.
-What time's he coming to see you?
-After 8:00.
All right, Miss Wonderly.
We'll have a man there.
I'll look after it myself.
Oh, thank you.
Oh, yes.
Will that be enough?
-Thank you.
-Not at all.
It'll help some if you meet Thursby
in the lobby.
-I will.
-You don't have to look for me.
-I'll see you all right.
-Thank you.
-Thank you so much.
-Goodbye.
They're right enough.
They have brothers in her bag.
-What do you think of her?
-Oh, she's sweet.
Maybe you saw her first, Sam,
but I spoke first.
You've got brains.
Yes, you have.
SPADE:
Hello?
Yeah. Speaking.
Miles Archer dead?
Where?
Bush and Stockton?
Yeah.
In 15 minutes.
Thanks.
Hello, Effie?
It's me.
Now, listen, precious.
Miles has been shot.
[EFFIE SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY]
Yeah. Dead.
Now, don't get excited.
Yeah.
Now, you'll have to break the news to Iva.
I'd fry first.
And keep her away from me.
That's a good girl.
Now get right over there.
You're an angel.
Bye.
-What do you want here?
-I'm Sam Spade. Tom Polhaus phoned.
Oh, I didn't know you at first.
They're back there.
POLHAUS: Hello, Sam. I figured you'd want
to see it before we took him away.
-Well, thanks, Tom. What happened?
-Got him right through the pump with this.
It's a Webley.
English, ain't it?
Yeah. A Webley-Fosbery .45 automatic,
eight shot. They don't make them anymore.
-How many gone out of it?
-Just one.
SPADE:
Let's see. Shot up here, huh?
Standing like you are,
with his back to the fence.
The man who shot him stood here.
He went over, taking the top of the fence.
Went on down the hill
and got caught on that rock.
That's it. The blast burnt his coat.
-Who found him?
-Man on the beat.
-Anybody hear the shot?
-Somebody must've. We just got here.
You want to go down
and have a look at him?
No, you've seen everything I could.
His gun was tucked away.
Hadn't been fired.
His overcoat was buttoned.
I found a $100 bill in his vest pocket
and 30-some bucks in his pants.
Was he working, Sam?
Well?
-Yeah, he was tailing a guy named Thursby.
-What for?
What for?
He wanted to find out where he lived.
Don't crowd me, Tom.
I'm going on down and break the news
to Miles' wife.
It's tough, him getting it like that,
ain't it?
Miles had his faults, like any of us...
...but I guess he must've had
some good points too, huh?
I guess so.
Miss Wonderly, please.
Uh? Checked out? What time?
Any forwarding address?
Thanks.
SPADE: Oh, hello, Tom.
Hello, lieutenant. Come in.
Sit down.
Drink?
Did you break the news
to Miles' wife, Sam?
-Uh-huh.
-How'd she take it?
-I don't know anything about women.
-Since when?
-What kind of a gun do you carry?
-None. I don't like them.
-Course, there are some at the office.
-You don't have one here?
-You sure about that?
-Look around.
Turn the dump upside down.
I won't
squawk, if you got a search warrant.
-We don't wanna--
-What are you birds sucking around for?
Tell me or get out.
You can't treat us like that.
It ain't right. We got our work to do.
Why were you tailing Thursby?
Miles was, and for the simple reason
we had a client--
-Who's the client?
-Sorry, I can't tell you that.
Be reasonable, Sam.
Give us a break, will you?
How we gonna turn up anything
if you don't tell us what you got?
Tom says you were in too much of a hurry
to stop and look at your dead partner.
And you didn't go to Archer's house
to tell his wife.
We called your office and the girl there
said you told her to do it.
I'll give you 10 minutes to get a phone
and do your talking to the girl.
I'll give you 10 minutes to get
to Thursby's. Geary and Leavenworth.
-You could do it easily.
-What's your boyfriend getting at, Tom?
Just this, Thursby was shot down
in front of his hotel...
...about a half an hour
after you left Bush Street.
-Keep your paws off me.
-What time did you get home?
Just a few minutes ahead of you.
I was walking around, thinking.
We know you weren't here.
Where did you walk to?
-Up Bush Street.
-You see anybody--?
SPADE:
No. No witnesses.
Well, I know where I stand, now.
Sorry I got up on my hind legs,
but you
fellas trying to rope me made me nervous.
Miles getting bumped off upset me,
and then you birds cracking foxy.
It's all right,
now I know what it's all about.
Forget it, Sam.
-Thursby die?
-Yeah.
How'd I kill him? I forget.
He was shot in the back four times
with a .44 or .45 from across the street.
Nobody saw it, but that's how it figures.
-Hotel people know anything?
-Nothing, except that he lived there a week.
-Alone?
-Yeah, alone.
Did you find out who he was?
What his game was? Well, did you?
-We thought you could tell us that.
-I've never seen Thursby, dead or alive.
Well, you know me, Spade.
If you did it, or if you didn't...
...you'll get a square deal
and most of the breaks.
Don't know as I'd blame you much.
The man that killed your partner.
But that won't stop me from nailing you.
Fair enough.
But I'd feel better about it
if you'd have a drink with me.
Success to crime.
EFFIE:
She's in there.
I told you to keep her away from me.
Yes, but you didn't tell me how.
Oh, don't be cranky with me, Sam.
I've had her all night.
Sorry, angel. I didn't mean--
Hello, Iva.
Oh, Sam.
Darling.
Effie take care of everything?
I think so.
Sam, did you kill him?
Who put that bright idea in your head?
Well, I thought you said
if it wasn't for Miles, you'd....
Be kind to me, Sam.
"You killed my husband, Sam.
Be kind to me."
Don't, Iva. Don't.
You shouldn't have come here today,
darling. You ought to be home.
You'll come soon?
Soon as I can.
Goodbye, Iva.
EFFIE:
Well?
How did you and the widow make out?
-She thinks I shot Miles.
-So you could marry her?The cops think I killed Thursby,
the guy
Miles was tailing for that Wonderly dame.
Who do you think I shot?
Are you going to marry Iva?
Don't be silly.
I wish I'd never laid eyes on her.
Do you suppose
she could have killed him?
You're an angel.
A nice, rattlebrained little angel.
-Oh, am I?
-Thanks, honey.
Suppose I told you Iva
hadn't been home many minutes...
...when I arrived to break the news
at 3:00 this morning?
Are you telling me?
She kept me waiting
while she undressed.
Her clothes were on a chair where she'd
dumped them, hat and coat underneath.
Her slip, on top, was still warm.
She'd wrinkled the bed,
but the wrinkles weren't mashed down.
You're a detective, darling,
but she didn't kill him.
Do the police really think
you shot this what's-his-name?
Do they? Look at me, Sam.
You worry me.
You think you know what you're doing,
but you're too slick for your own good.
Someday you're going to find it out.
Spade and Archer.
Oh, yes, Miss Wonderly.
Hello?
Yeah, this is Sam Spade.
Where?
Coronet Apartments, California Avenue,
apartment 1001.
What's the name? Miss LeBlanc.
Okay, I'll be right over.
Oh, have Miles' desk
moved out of the office...
...and have "Spade and Archer" taken off
all the doors and windows...
...and have "Samuel Spade" put on.
Oh, come in, Mr. Spade.
Everything's upside down.
I haven't finished unpacking. Sit down.
Mr. Spade, I....
I have a terrible,
terrible confession to make.
That story I told you yesterday...
...was just a story.
Oh, that. Well, we didn't exactly
believe your story, Miss....
What is your name, Wonderly or LeBlanc?
It's really O'Shaughnessy.
Brigid O'Shaughnessy.
We didn't believe your story,
Miss O'Shaughnessy.
-We believed your $200.
-You mean that....
You paid us more
than if you'd been telling the truth...
...and enough more to make it all right.
Tell me, Mr. Spade,
am I to blame for last night?
You warned us
that Thursby was dangerous.
Of course, you lied to us about your sister,
but we didn't believe you.
No, I wouldn't say that you were at fault.
Thank you.
Mr. Archer was so alive yesterday...
-...so solid and hearty, and--
-Stop it.
He knew what he was doing.
Those are the chances we take.
Was he married?
Yeah, with 10,000 insurance, no children
and a wife that didn't like him.
-Please don't.
-That's the way it was.
Anyway, there's no time for worrying
about that now.
Out there's a flock of policemen
and assistant district attorneys...
...running around with their noses
to the ground.
Mr. Spade, do they know about me?
Not yet. I've been stalling them
until I could see you.
Do they have to know?
Can't you shield me
so I won't have to answer their questions?
Maybe, but I gotta know
what it's all about.
I can't tell you.
I can't tell you now.
I will later, when I can.
You've got to trust me, Mr. Spade.
Oh, I'm so alone and afraid.
I've got nobody to help me
if you won't help me.
Be generous, Mr. Spade.
You're brave. You're strong.
You can spare me
some of that courage and strength, surely.
Help me, Mr. Spade.
I need help so badly.
I have no right to ask you.
I know I haven't, but I do ask you.
Help me.
You won't need much of anybody's help.
You're good.
It's chiefly your eyes, I think,
and that throb you get in your voice...
...when you say things like,
"Be generous, Mr. Spade."
I deserve that.
But the lie was in the way I said it,
not at all in what I said.
It's my own fault
if you can't believe me now.
Now you are dangerous.
But I'm not going to be able
to be of much help to you...
...unless I've got some idea
what it's all about.
For instance, I've gotta have some sort
of a line on your Floyd Thursby.
I met him in the Orient.
We came here from Hong Kong last week.
He promised to help me.
He took advantage of my dependence
to betray me.
Betray you? How?
Why did you want him shadowed?
I wanted to find out how far he'd gone,
whom he was meeting, things like that.
-Did he kill Archer?
-Certainly.
He had a Luger in his shoulder holster.
Archer wasn't shot with a Luger.
Mr. Spade, you don't think I had anything
to do with the death of Mr. Archer?
-Did you?
-No.
That's good.
Floyd always carried an extra revolver
in his overcoat pocket.
Why all the guns?
He lived by them.
The story is that
he first came to the Orient...
...as bodyguard to a gambler
who'd had to leave the States.
The gambler had disappeared. Floyd knew
about the disappearance.
I don't know.
I do know he always went heavily armed,
and that he never went to sleep...
...without covering the floor around his bed
with crumpled newspapers...
...so that nobody could come
silently into his room.
You picked a nice sort of a playmate.
Only that sort could have helped me,
if he'd been loyal.
-How bad a spot are you actually in?
-Bad as could be.
Physical danger?
I'm not heroic. I don't think
there's anything worse than death.
-Then it's that?
-It's that, as surely as we're sitting here.
Unless you help me.
Who killed Thursby, your enemies or his?
I don't know.
His, I suppose.
I'm afraid. I don't know.
This is hopeless.
I don't know what you want done.
-I don't even know if you know.
-You won't go to the police?
Go to them? All I gotta do is stand still,
they'll be all over me.
I'll tell them all I know,
and you'll take your chances.
You've been patient with me.
You've tried to help me.
It's useless and hopeless, I suppose.
I do thank you for what you've done.
I'll have to take my chances.
How much money have you got?
I've got about $500 left.
Give it to me.
-There's only $400 here.
-I had to keep some to live on.
-Well, can't you get some more?
-No.
Got anything
you can raise some money on?
-I've got some furs and a little jewelry.
-You'll have to hock them.
There you are.
I'll be back as soon as I can
with the best news I can manage.
I'll ring four times.
Long, short, long, short.
And no, you needn't bother
to come to the door. I'll let myself in.
Anything stirring?
Did you send the flowers?
You're invaluable, darling. Say,
get my lawyer on the phone, will you?
Hello, Sid?
I think I'm going to have to tell a coroner
to go to blazes, Sid.
Can I hide behind the sanctity
of my client's identity...
...secrets and what-nots
all the same, priest or lawyer?
Yeah, but Dundy's getting rambunctious
and maybe it is a bit thick this time.
Yeah. What'll it cost
to be on the safe side?
Well, maybe it's worth it.
Okay, go ahead.
Gardenia.
Quick, darling, in with him.
Will you come in, Mr. Cairo?
Will you sit down, Mr. Cairo?
Thank you, sir.
Now, what can I do for you, Mr. Cairo?
May a stranger offer condolences
for your partner's unfortunate death?
Thanks.
Is there, Mr. Spade,
as the newspapers imply...
...a certain relationship
between that unfortunate happening...
...and the death a little later
of the man Thursby?
I beg your pardon. No.
More than idle curiosity prompted
my question.
See, Mr. Spade, I'm trying to recover...
...an ornament that, shall we say,
has been mislaid.
-Uh-huh.
-I thought and hoped you could assist me.
The ornament is a statuette.
A black figure of a bird.
I am prepared to pay,
on behalf of the figure's rightful owner...
...the sum of $5,000 for its recovery.
I am prepared to promise that--
What is the phrase?
No questions will be asked.
$5,000 is a lot of money.
Yes, Effie?
No, that'll be all. Just be sure to lock
the door behind you on your way out.
Good night.
$5,000 is--
Clasp your hands together
at the back of your neck.
I intend to search your offices,
Mr. Spade.
I warn you, if you attempt to prevent me,
I shall certainly shoot you.
Go ahead and search.
Will you please come
to the center of the room?
Well, I have to make certain
that you are not armed.
Look what you did to my shirt.
Sorry.
But imagine my embarrassment
when I found out that $5,000 offer...
-...was just hooey.
-Mr. Spade, my offer is genuine.
I am prepared to pay $5,000
for the figure's return.
-Do you have it?
-No.
But if it isn't here...
...why did you risk injury
to prevent my searching for it?
Why should I sit around here
and let people come in and stick me up?
But certainly it is only natural
that I try to save the owner...
...such a considerable expense,
if possible.
Who is he?
Mr. Spade, you'll forgive
my not answering that question.
Well, I think we'd be better off all around
if we'd put our cards on the table.
No, I do not think it would be better.
You see, Mr. Spade,
if you know more than I do...
...then I shall profit by your knowledge.
So will you, to the extent of $5,000.
Well, there's nothing like $5,000 here.
Oh, you want some assurance
of my sincerity?
-A retainer? Would that do?
-It might.
You will take, say, $100?
No. I will take, say, $200.
Let's see, your first guess was
that I had the bird.
There's nothing to that.
What's your second guess?
That you know where it is, or at least
you know it is where you can get it.
You're not hiring me to do any murders
or burglaries...
...but simply to get it back if possible,
in an honest, lawful way?
If possible.
But in any case, with discretion.
When you wish to contact me, sir,
I'm staying at the Hotel Belvedere.
Room 635.
I sincerely expect
the greatest mutual benefit...
...from our association, Mr. Spade.
Oh, may I please have my gun, now?
Oh, sure. I'd forgotten all about it.
Will you please clasp your hands together
at the back of your neck?
I intend to search your offices.
Well, I'll be.
Why, sure.
Go ahead. I won't stop you.
-Turn to the right and go up the hill, driver.
-Okay.
Mr. Spade.
Do you bring any news?
Did you manage it so that
the police won't have to know about me?
Well, they won't for a while, anyway.
You are wonderful.
You won't get into any trouble, will you?
SPADE: I don't mind a reasonable amount
of trouble.
Do sit down.
You, uh....
You aren't exactly the sort of a person
you pretend to be, are you?
Why, I'm not sure I know exactly
what you mean.
The schoolgirl manner. You know,
blushing, stammering and all that.
I haven't lived a good life. I've been bad.
Worse than you could know.
That's good, because if you actually
were as innocent as you pretend to be...
...we'd never get anywhere.
I won't be innocent.
Good.
Oh, by the way, I saw Joel Cairo tonight.
-Do you know him?
-Only slightly.
You're good. You're very good.
-What did he say?
-About what?
-About me.
-Nothing.
-What did you talk about then?
-He offered me $5,000 for the black bird.
You're not gonna go around straightening
things
and poking the fire again, are you?
No, I'm not.
-What did you say?
-I said $5,000 was a lot of money.
It is.
It's more than I can ever offer you
if I have to bid for your loyalty.
That's good coming from you.
What have you ever given me
beside money?
You ever given me any of your confidence,
any of the truth?
Haven't you tried to buy my loyalty
with money and nothing else?
What else is there I can buy you with?
I don't care what your secrets are...
...but I can't go ahead without
more confidence in you than I've got now.
You've got to convince me that you aren't
fiddling around...
...hoping it'll all come out right
in the end.
-Can't you trust me a little longer?
-What are you waiting for?
I've got to talk to Joel Cairo.
You can see him tonight.
He's at the theater. It'll be out soon.
-I'll leave a message at his hotel.
-He can't come here.
I can't let him know where I am.
I'm afraid.
My place, then.
Hello?
-I want to leave a message for Joel Cairo.
-All right.
I never would've placed myself in this
position
if I didn't trust you completely.
That again?
Do you know that's true, though?
You don't have to trust me, so long
as you can persuade me to trust you.
But don't worry about that now.
He'll be along any minute.
You get your business with Cairo over with,
then we'll see how we stand.
And you'll let me go about it with him
in my own way?
SPADE:
Oh, sure.
You are a godsend.
Well, now don't overdo it.
Mr. Spade, there is a boy outside.
He seems to be watching the house.
Yeah, I know. I spotted him.
What? What's that? What boy?
I don't know. A kid.
He's been trailing me all evening.
-Did he follow you to my apartment?
-I shook him long before that.
Come in, Mr. Cairo.
-I'm delighted to see you again, madam.
-I was sure you would be, Joel.
Mr. Spade told me about your offer
for the falcon.
-How soon can you have the money?
-The money is ready.
O'SHAUGHNESSY: In cash?
-Oh, yes.
You're ready to pay $5,000
if we turn over the falcon to you?
Excuse me, please.
I must have expressed myself badly.
I did not mean to say
that I have the money in my pocket...
...but I am ready to get it for you
on a minute's notice...
...anytime during banking hours.
That's probably true.
He only had a couple of hundred...
...when I searched him this afternoon
at my office.
I shall be able to have the money for you
at, say, half past 10 in the morning.
But I haven't got the falcon.
I'll have it in another week
at the most, though.
Then where is it?
-Where Floyd hid it.
-Floyd hid....
And you know where he hid it?
Then why do we have to wait a week?
Oh, perhaps not a whole week.
And why, if I may ask another question,
are you willing to sell it to me?
Because I'm afraid.
After what happened to Floyd...
...I'm afraid to touch it,
except to turn it over to somebody.
What exactly did happen to Floyd?
The fat man.
Fat man.
-Is he here?
O'SHAUGHNESSY: I don't know.
I suppose so.
What difference does it make?
It might make a world of difference.
Or you or me.
Precisely. But, shall we add,
more certainly the boy outside?
Yes. But you might be able
to get around him, Joel...
...as you did the one in Istanbul.
What was his name?
You mean the one you couldn't get
to come to--
This is the second time
that you have laid hands on me.
When you're slapped,
you'll take it and like it.
Who's that?
I don't know. Keep quiet.
SPADE:
Hello.
You guys pick swell hours
to do your visiting in.
-What is it?
-We want to talk to you, Spade.
-Go ahead and talk.
-We don't have to do it in the hall, do we?
-You can't come in.
-Oh, come off it now, Sam.
You aren't trying to strong-arm me,
are you, Tom?
Why don't you be reasonable?
It would pay you to play along with us.
You got away with this and that...
...but you can't keep it up.
-Stop me when you can.
-That's what I intend to do.
There's talk going around
about you and Archer's wife.
-Is there anything to it?
-Not a thing.
The talk is she tried to get a divorce
so she
could put in with you. He wouldn't give it.
-Anything to that?
-No.
There's talk that that's why
he was put on the spot.
Don't be a hog, Dundy.
Your idea that I killed Thursby
because he killed Miles...
...falls to pieces if you blame me
for killing Miles.
You haven't heard me say
you killed anybody.
-You're the one bringing that up.
-Haven't you anything better to do than to keep popping in here every
morning,
asking fool questions?
-And getting a lot of lying answers.
-Take it easy.
If you say there's nothing between
you and Archer's wife,
you're a liar.
Is that the hot tip that brought you
up here at this ungodly hour?
-That's one of them.
-And the other?
Let us in.
All right, Spade, we'll go.
Maybe you're right in bucking us.
Think it over.
[THUDDING]
CAIRO:
Help!
-I guess we're going in.
-I guess you are.
DUNDY:
What's going on in here?
CAIRO:
Look. Look, officer. Look what she did.
-Did you do that?
O'SHAUGHNESSY: I had to.
I was alone with him.
He tried to attack me.
I couldn't bring myself to shoot him.
You dirty, filthy liar, you. It isn't true.
I came up here in good faith,
and then both of them attacked me.
And then when he went out to talk to you,
he left her here with a pistol.
She said as soon as you leave,
they are going to kill me...
...so I called for help
because I didn't want you to leave.
And then she struck me with a pistol.
O'SHAUGHNESSY:
Why don't you make him tell the truth?
CAIRO: Look. Look what she....
-Behave yourself, sister.
That's no way to act.
I don't guess we'll be wrong
running the lot of them in.
Don't be in a hurry.
Everything can be explained.
I'll bet.
Miss O'Shaughnessy, may I present
Lieutenant Dundy and Detective Polhaus?
Miss O'Shaughnessy is an operative
in my employ since yesterday.
That's a lie too.
That is Mr. Joel Cairo.
Cairo was an acquaintance of Thursby's.
He came into my office late this afternoon...
...hired me to find something that
Thursby was supposed to have on him.
It looked funny to me the way he put it,
so I wouldn't touch it.
Then he pulled a gun on me.
Well, that's neither here nor there...
...unless we start preferring charges
against each other.
Miss O'Shaughnessy and I
discussed the matter...
...and decided to find out
how much he knew...
...about Miles' and Thursby's killings,
so we asked him to come up here.
Now, maybe we did put the questions
to him a little roughly.
You know how that is, lieutenant.
But we didn't hurt him enough
to make him cry for help.
-What have you got to say to that?
-I don't know what to say.
Try telling the facts.
-What? Facts?
-Oh, quit stalling.
All you have to do is swear out
a complaint
and I'll throw them in the can.
Go ahead, Cairo. Tell him, he'll do it.
Then we'll swear out a complaint
against you, and he'll have the lot of us.
Get your hats.
Well, boys and girls,
we put it over nicely.
-Go on, get your hats.
-Don't you know when you're being kidded?
No, but that can wait
till we get down to the hall.
Wake up, Dundy, you're being kidded.
When I heard the buzzer, I said
to Miss O'Shaughnessy and Cairo:
"There's the police.
They're getting to be a nuisance.
When you hear them going, scream.
We'll see how far we can string them
until they tumble."
Stop it, Sam.
That cut on his head.
How did that get there?
-Ask him. Maybe he cut himself shaving.
-The cut? No.
When we pretended to be struggling
for the gun, I fell over the carpet. I fell.
Horsefeathers.
Take him along, anyway,
for packing a gun.
Don't be a sap.
That gun was a plant.
It was one of mine.
Too bad it was only a .25.
You could prove that was the gun...
...Miles and Thursby were shot with.
-No, Sam. No.
-Well, then get him out of here.
-Get their names and addresses.
-My name is Joel Cairo, Hotel Belvedere.
Miss O'Shaughnessy's address
is my office.
-Where do you live?
-Get him out of here.
Take it easy, will you?
Is that all you want?
-Yeah.
-I think I'll be going now.
What's the hurry, Cairo?
There is no hurry.
It's getting quite late, and....
Tell him to leave the gun.
I hope you know
what you're doing, Sam.
You're absolutely the wildest, most
unpredictable person I've ever known.
Do you always carry on so high-handed?
Well, you've had your talk with Cairo.
Now you can talk to me.
Oh, yes, of course.
I'm listening.
I'm still listening.
-Oh, look at the time. I must be going.
-Oh, no. Not till you've told me all about it.
Am I a prisoner?
Maybe the boy outside
hasn't gone home yet.
Do you suppose he's still there?
Likely.
You can start now.
You are the most insistent person.
And wild and unpredictable, huh?
Say, what's this bird, this falcon
that everybody's all steamed up about?
Supposing I wouldn't tell you
anything about it at all?
What would you do?
Something wild and unpredictable?
I might.
It's a black figure, as you know,
smooth and shiny...
...of a bird, a hawk or falcon,
about that high.
Oh, here.
-What--? What makes it so important?
-I don't know. They wouldn't tell me.
They offered me ￡500 if I'd help them
get it away from the man who had it.
That was in Istanbul?
Marmara.
Go ahead.
But that's all.
They promised me ￡500 if I'd help them,
and I did.
Then we found out that Joel Cairo
intended to desert us...
...taking the falcon with him
and leaving Floyd and me nothing.
So we did exactly that to him.
Then I wasn't any better off
than before.
Floyd hadn't any intention
of keeping his promise...
...about sharing.
I learned that by the time we got here.
What's the bird made of?
Porcelain or black stone. I don't know.
I only saw it for a few minutes.
Floyd showed it to me
when we first got hold of it.
You are a liar.
I am.
I've always been a liar.
Don't brag about it.
Was there any truth at all in that yarn?
Some.
Not very much.
Well, we got all night.
Coffee'll be ready soon.
We'll have a cup and try again.
Oh, I'm so tired.
So tired of lying and making up lies.
Not knowing what is a lie
and what's the truth. I wish....
I want to talk to Mr. Cairo, Joel Cairo.
Oh. Thanks.
Where is he?
-What?
-Where is he?
-Who?
-Cairo.
What do you think you're doing, Jack,
kidding me?
I'll tell you when I am.
New York, aren't you?
Shove off.
You're gonna have to talk to me
before you're through.
Some of you will,
and you can tell the fat man I said so.
Keep asking for it
and you're gonna get it. Plenty.
I told you to shove off.
Shove off.
People lose teeth talking like that.
You wanna hang around,
you'll be polite.
Luke.
-Hello, Sam.
-Hello, Luke.
Say, that was too bad about Miles.
Yeah. It was a tough break.
I want to show you something.
What do you let these cheap gunmen
hang around for...
...with their heaters
bulging in their clothes?
What do you want here?
Well, if you don't want anything, beat it
and don't come back.
I won't forget you guys.
-What is it?
-I don't know. I just spotted him.
-Say, what about Miles?
-I'll see you, Luke.
- 603
-Six-oh-three.
-Yes, sir.
Good morning.
-Good morning.
-There you are.
Let's go someplace where we can talk.
Our conversations have not been
such that
I'm anxious to continue them.
Forgive my speaking so bluntly,
but it is the truth.
You mean last night?
I had to throw in with her.
I don't know where the bird is. She does.
How we gonna get it if I don't play along?
You always have a very smooth
explanation ready, huh?
What do you want me to do?
Learn to stutter?
Dundy take you to the station?
How long they work on you?
Till a little while ago.
-What'd they shake out of you?
-Shake out? Not one thing.
I adhered to the course you indicated
earlier in your rooms...
...but I certainly wish you would have
invented a more reasonable story.
I felt distinctly like an idiot repeating it.
Don't worry about the story's goofiness.
A sensible one would have
had us all in the cooler.
-You sure you didn't tell them anything?
-I did not.
Now, you'll want sleep
if you've been
standing up under a police grilling all night.
See you later.
No, not yet.
Yes, I'll have him call you
the minute he comes in.
That's the third time she's called
this morning.
-Miss O'Shaughnessy's in there.
-Anything else?
The district attorney's office called.
Bryan would like to see you.
And a Mr. Gutman called.
When I told him you weren't in...
...he said, "Tell him the young man...
...gave me his message,
and that I phoned and will phone again?"
Gutman, huh?
Thanks, darling.
Darling. Somebody's been in my apartment.
It's all upside down, every which way.
I changed as fast as I could
and came right over here.
-You must have let that boy follow you.
-No, angel.
I shook him off
long before I ever went to your place.
It might have been Cairo.
He wasn't at the hotel last night.
He told me he'd been standing up
under a police grilling. I wonder.
-You saw Joel this morning?
-Yeah.
Why?
Because I've gotta keep
in some sort of touch...
...with all the loose ends of this dizzy affair
if I'm ever gonna make heads or tails of it.
Now we've got to find
a new home for you.
I won't go back there.
I got an idea. Wait a minute.
What does your woman's intuition
tell you about her?
She's all right. Maybe it's her own fault
for being in trouble, but she's all right.
Are you strong enough for her
to put her up for a few days?
-You mean at home?
-Yeah.
-Is she in any danger, Sam?
-I think she is.
Gee, that'd scare Mom
into a green hemorrhage.
I'd have to say she's a surprise witness
you're keeping undercover.
You're a darling.
Oh, Brigid.
Effie offered to put you up
for a few days.
That's very kind.
You'd better start now. Go out the back.
There's usually a cab parked there.
Ride partway with her
and make sure you're not followed.
Change cabs a couple of times,
just to be safe.
I'll give Mom a ring.
There's time enough for that
when you get back.
I'll call you later.
Hello?
This is Samuel Spade.
Say, my secretary tells me
Mr. Bryan wants to see me.
Yeah. Ask him what time's
most convenient for him.
Spade. S-P-A-D-E.
Hello, honey.
Yeah.
Two-thirty. All right. Thanks.
Oh, Sam, forgive me. Please forgive me.
I sent those policemen
to your place last night.
I was mad, crazy with jealousy.
I phoned that if they went there
they'd learn something about Miles' murder.
-What made you think of that?
-I was mad. I wanted to hurt you.
Did you tell them who you were?
-No. Sam, dearest, I--
-Where'd you phone from?
-The drugstore across from your place.
-You better hurry home...and think of something
to tell the police.
And by the way...
...where were you the night
Miles was murdered?
Home.
-I was.
-No.
But if that's your story,
it's all right with me.
Now you run along.
Hello?
Yeah, this is Spade.
Oh, yes, Mr. Gutman, I got it.
I've been waiting to hear from you.
Well, now. The sooner, the better.
Say, 15 minutes? Right.
Twelve-C.
Twelve-C to your left, sir.
-Mr. Spade.
-How do you do, Mr. Gutman?
You begin well, sir.
I distrust a man who says when.
He's got to be careful
not to drink too much...
...because he's not to be trusted
when he does.
Well, sir...
...here's to plain speaking
and clear understanding.
-You're a close-mouthed man?
-No, I like to talk.
Better and better.
I distrust a close-mouthed man.
He generally picks the wrong time to talk
and says the wrong things.
Talking's something you can't do
judiciously unless you keep in practice.
Now, sir. We'll talk, if you like.
I'll tell you right out. I am a man who likes
talking to a man who likes to talk.
Swell.
Will we talk about the black bird?
[CHUCKLES]
You're a man for me, sir.
No beating about the bush.
Right to the point.
Let's talk about the black bird,
by all means.
But first, answer me a question.
Are you here
as Miss O'Shaughnessy's representative?
Well, there's nothing certain either way.
It depends.
Depends on?
Maybe it depends on Joel Cairo.
Maybe.
The question is then which you represent.
It'll be one or the other.
I didn't say so.
-Who else is there?
-There's me.
Ah. Ha-ha.
That's wonderful, sir, wonderful.
I do like a man who tells you right out
he's looking out for himself.
Don't we all?
I don't trust a man who says he's not.
Uh-huh. Now, let's talk
about the black bird.
Let's.
Mr. Spade, have you any conception...
...of how much money can be got
for that black bird?
No.
Well, sir, if I told you,
if I told you half, you'd call me a liar.
No, not even if I thought so.
But you tell me what it is,
and I'll figure out the profit.
You mean, you don't know
what the bird is?
Oh, I know
what it's supposed to look like...
...and I know the value in human life
you people put on it.
She didn't tell you what it is?
-Cairo didn't, either?
-He offered me 10,000 for it.
Ten thousand.
Dollars, mind you, not even pounds.
Do they know what that bird is, sir?
What is your impression?
Not much to go by.
Cairo didn't say he did, didn't say he didn't.
She said she didn't,
but I took it for granted she was lying.
Not an injudicious thing to do.
If they don't know, I'm the only one
in the whole wide sweet world who does.
Swell. When you've told me,
that'll make two of us.
Mathematically correct, sir, but I don't
know for certain that I'm going to tell you.
Don't be foolish. I know where it is.
That's why I'm here.
Well, sir, where is it?
You see, I must tell you what I know,
but you won't tell me what you know.
It's hardly equitable, sir.
No, no. I don't think we can do business
along those lines.
Well, think again, and think fast.
I told that gunsel you'd
talk to me before you're through.
You'll talk to me today,
or you are through.
What are you wasting my time for?
I can get along without you.
And
keep that gunsel out of my way
while you're making up your mind.
I'll kill him if you don't. I'll kill him.
Well, sir, I must say
you have a most violent temper.
SPADE:
Think it over. You've got till 5:00.
Then you're either in or out, for keeps.
-Who killed Thursby?
SPADE: I don't know.
Perhaps, but you could make
an excellent guess.
My guess might be excellent or crummy,
but Mrs. Spade didn't raise any children...
...dippy enough to make guesses in front
of a district attorney and a stenographer.
Why, if you've nothing to conceal?
Everybody has something to conceal.
I'm a sworn officer of the law,
24 hours a day...
...and neither formality nor informality
justifies you withholding...
...evidence of crime from me except,
of course, on constitutional grounds.
Both you and the police
have accused me...
...of being mixed up in the murders.
I've had trouble with both of you
before, and as far as I can see...
...my best chance of clearing myself
of the trouble...
...is bringing in the murderers
all tied up.
The only chance I've got of tying them up
and bringing them in...
...is by staying away from you
and the police.
You'd gum up the works.
You getting
this all right? Am I going too fast?
No, sir. I'm getting it all right.
Good work. If you want to go to the board
and tell them I'm obstructing justice...
...and ask them to revoke my license,
hop to it.
You tried it before,
and it didn't get you anything.
-Now, look here.
-I don't want any more informal talks.
I've nothing to say to you,
and I'm tired of being called things...
...by every crackpot on the city payroll.
So, if you want to see me...
...pinch me or subpoena me or something,
and I'll come down with my lawyer.
I'll see you at the inquest, maybe.
Come on. He wants to see you.
I didn't expect you till 5:25.
I hope I haven't kept you waiting.
Keep on riding me,
they're gonna be
picking iron out of your liver.
[SPADE CHUCKLES]
The cheaper the crook,
the gaudier the patter, huh?
Now, let's go.
Come on.
This'll put you in solid with your boss.
Come in, sir. Thank you for coming.
Come in.
You shouldn't let him go around
with these on him.
He might get himself hurt.
Well, well, what's this?
A crippled newsie took them away
from him. I made him give them back.
By gad, sir, you're a chap worth knowing.
An amazing character. Give me your hat.
Sit down.
-I owe you an apology, sir.
SPADE: Now, never mind that.
Let's talk about the black bird.
All right, sir, let's.
Let's.
This is going to be the most astounding
thing you've ever heard of, sir.
I say this knowing that a man
of your caliber and profession...
...must have known
some astounding things in his time.
What do you know about the Order
of the Hospital of Saint John of Jerusalem...
...later known as the Knights of Rhodes?
-Crusaders or something, weren't they?
-Very good. Sit down.
In 1539, these crusading knights...
...persuaded Emperor Charles V
to give them the island of Malta.
He made but one condition,
that they pay
him each year the tribute of a falcon...
...in acknowledgement that Malta
was still under Spain.
-Do you follow me?
-Uh-huh.
Have you any conception of the extreme,
the immeasurable wealth of the Order?
-I imagine they were pretty well fixed.
-"Pretty well" is putting it mildly.
They were rolling in wealth, sir.
For years they'd taken from the East
nobody knows what spoils of gems...
...precious metals, silks, ivory, sir.
We all know the holy wars to them
were largely a matter of loot.
The knights were profoundly grateful
to the Emperor Charles...
...for his generosity toward them.
They hit upon the thought of sending him
for his first year's tribute...
...not an insignificant live bird...
...but a glorious golden falcon
crusted from head to foot...
...with the finest jewels in their coffers.
-Well, sir,
what do you think of that?
-I don't know.
These are facts, historical facts.
Not schoolbook history, not Mr. Wells'
history, but history, nevertheless.
They sent this jeweled bird to Charles,
who was then in Spain.
They sent it in a galley commanded
by a member of the Order.
It never reached Spain.
A famous admiral of buccaneers
took the knights' galley and the bird.
In 1713, it turned up in Sicily.
In 1840, it appeared in Paris.
It had, by that time,
acquired a coat of black enamel...
...so that it looked nothing more
than a fairly interesting black statuette.
In that disguise, sir, it was,
as you may say, kicked around Paris...
...for over three score years
by private owners too stupid...
...to see what it was under the skin.
Then, heh-heh,
in 1923,
a Greek dealer
named Charilaos Konstantinides
...found it in an obscure shop.
No thickness of enamel
could conceal value from his eyes.
-You begin to believe me a little?
-I haven't said I didn't.
Well, sir, to hold it safe while pursuing
his researches into its history...
...Charilaos re-enameled the bird.
Despite this precaution, however,
I got wind of his find.
If I'd only known a few days sooner.
I was in London
when I heard. I packed
a bag, got on the boat train immediately.
On the train I opened the paper,
and read that Charilaos' establishment...
...had been burglarized
and him murdered.
Sure enough, on arriving there,
I discovered the bird was gone.
That was 17 years ago.
Well, sir, it took me 17 years
to locate that bird, but I did.
I wanted it.
I'm a man not easily discouraged
when I want something.
I traced it to the home
of a Russian general, one Kemidov...
...in an Istanbul suburb.
He didn't know a thing about it.
It was nothing
but a black-enameled figure to him...
...but his contrariness kept him
from selling it...
...when I made him an offer.
So I sent him some agents to get it.
Well, sir,
they got it and I haven't got it.
But I'm going to get it.
Your glass.
Then the bird doesn't really belong
to any of you, but to a General Kemidov?
Well, sir, you might as well say
it belonged to the King of Spain.
I don't see how you can honestly grant
anyone else a clear title to it...
...except by right of possession.
And now, sir...
...before we start to talk prices,
how soon
can you, or how soon are you willing...
-...to produce the falcon?
-Couple of days.
That is satisfactory.
Well, sir, here's to a fair bargain.
Profits large enough for both of us.
What's your idea of a fair bargain?
I will give you $25,000
when you deliver the falcon to me...
...and another 25,000 later on.
Or I will give you one quarter
of what I realize on the falcon.
That would amount to a greater sum.
-How much greater?
-Who knows? Shall we say 100,000?
Would you believe me if I name a sum
that seems probable?
Why not?
What would you say
to a quarter of a million?
Then you think the dingus
is worth a million, huh?
In your own words, why not?
-That's a lot of dough.
-A lot of dough.
-Minimum, huh? What's the maximum?
-The maximum, I refuse to guess.
You'd think me crazy.
I don't know.
There's no telling
how high it could go, sir.
That is the one and only truth about it.
Wilmer.
Hello, Effie. It's me.
Let me talk to Miss O'Shaughnessy.
What? She didn't show up?
Oh.
You get on back to the office and
wait there till I come or you hear from me.
Yeah, let's do something right
for a change.
It started in the hold aft,
in the rear basement.
What insurance was she carrying?
-Anybody burnt?
-No.
Only the harbor watch was aboard.
-Someone I know came--
-Huh?
Someone I know came aboard
this afternoon...
...and I haven't seen her since.
I'm worried.
No reason to be, mister.
Everybody got off all right.
I wonder if you saw her.
She's kind of small, about 5-foot--
I couldn't tell you, mister. But if
she come aboard, she got off all right.
Only the harbor watch was aboard
when the fire started.
Now you know as much about it
as I do, precious.
Maybe they went down to the ship.
Maybe they didn't.
The part about the bird is thrilling.
Or ridiculous.
You know.
Falcon.
Lock that door.
Is...?
Is he...?
Yeah.
He couldn't have come far
with those holes in him.
Why couldn't he have stayed alive
long enough to tell us something?
Here, here, here, none of that now.
Come on.
-You can't pass out on me now.
-All right, Sam.
Do you really think it's...?
-We've got it, angel, we've got it.
-You're hurting me.
Answer the phone.
Hello.
[WOMAN SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY
OVER PHONE]
Yes. Who?
Oh, yes.
Where?
Yes, yes.
Hello? Hello. Hello.
That was Miss O'Shaughnessy.
She's in danger.
-Where is she?
-Burlingame, 26 Ancho.
Sam, her voice, it was awful.
Something happened to her
before she could finish. Go help her.
You've got to go to her.
He was helping her, and they killed him.
You've got to go, Sam.
All right, I'll go.
After I've gone,
you phone the police.
Tell them how it happened,
but don't drag names in.
I got the phone call and told you
I had to go, but didn't say where.
Forget this. Tell them how it happened,
without the bundle.
Get that straight. Everything
happened exactly as it did...
...but without the bundle,
and I got the phone call, not you.
-Yes, Sam.
-Okay.
Shut this door and lock it behind me.
Don't open it till the police come.
Do you know who he is?
Yeah. Yeah, he's Captain Jacoby,
master of the La Paloma.
You're a good man, sister.
-Can I borrow your pencil?
-Sure.
-Say, Frank.
-Oh, hello, Mr. Spade.
-You got plenty of gas?
-Sure thing.
Do you know where Ancho Street
is in Burlingame?
-Nope, but we can find her.
-Twenty-six is the number...
-...and the sooner the better.
-All right.
Keep your motor running.
-Bum steer, Mr. Spade?
-Yeah.
Let's get to a phone booth.
Hello, Mrs. Perine? Is Effie there?
Yes, please.
Hello, precious. What's the good news?
No, no. It was a bum steer.
Are you sure that was her voice?
Well, it was hooey.
Everything go all right?
Nothing said about the bundle, huh?
That's swell.
They take you down to the hall?
All right.
You better hit the hay and get
a good night's rest. You sound all in.
No, no. Save it till tomorrow.
I'm going on home.
-Thanks. Good night, Frank.
-Good night, Mr. Spade.
O'SHAUGHNESSY: I've been hiding
in a doorway up the street.
I thought you'd never come.
Can you make it,
or shall I carry you?
I'll be all right as soon as I can
get some place where I can lie down.
Well, sir, we're all here.
Now, let's come in and sit down
and be comfortable and talk.
SPADE:
Sure.
-Get away. You're not gonna frisk me.
-Stand still. Shut up.
Take your paws off me,
or I'll make you use that gun.
Ask your boss if he wants me shot up
before we talk.
Never mind, Wilmer.
You certainly are
a most headstrong individual.
Well, let's be seated.
Are you ready to make the first payment
and take the falcon off my hands?
Well, sir, as to that....
As to that....
Ten thousand? We were talking about
a lot more money than this.
Yes, sir, we were.
But this is genuine coin of the realm.
With a dollar of this,
you can buy $10 of talk.
And there are more of us
to be taken care of now.
That may be, but I've got the falcon.
I shouldn't think it necessary
to remind you, Mr. Spade...
...that you may have the falcon,
but we certainly have you.
I'm trying not to let that worry me.
We'll get back to the money later on.
There's something else
to be discussed first.
We've got to have a fall guy.
The police have gotta have a victim,
somebody they can pin those murders on.
Three? But there's only two, because
Thursby certainly killed your partner.
Only two, what difference does it make?
-We've got to give the police--
-Come, come, Mr. Spade.
You can't expect us to believe
at this late date...
...that you're the least bit afraid
of the police.
-Or that you're not able to handle--
-I'm in this up to my neck.
I've got to find somebody, a victim,
when the time comes. If I don't, I'll be it.
Let's give them the gunsel.
He actually did shoot Thursby and Jacoby,
didn't he?
Anyway, he's made to order for the part.
Look at him.
Let's give him to them.
By gad, sir, you are a character.
That you are.
There's never any telling
what you'll say or do next...
...except that it's bound
to be astonishing.
-It's our best bet. With him in their hands--
-My dear man, can't you see...
...that if I, even for a moment thought
of doing such a thing.... That's ridiculous.
I feel towards Wilmer here just exactly
as if he were my own son.
Really, I do.
But if I even for a moment
thought of doing what you propose...
...what in the world would keep Wilmer
from telling the police...
...every last detail
about the falcon and all--
Let him talk his head off.
I'll guarantee you
nobody'll do anything about it.
Well, well, what do you think of this,
Wilmer? Mighty funny.
Mighty funny.
How do you feel now?
Any better, precious?
[WHISPERING]
Much better.
But I'm frightened.
Well, don't be.
Nothing very bad's going to happen here.
You want a drink, angel?
Be careful, Sam.
Well?
If you're really serious,
the least we can do
in common politeness is hear you out.
Now, how would you be able to fix it
so that Wilmer couldn't do us any harm?
I can show our district attorney,
that if he goes around...
...trying to collect everybody,
he's gonna have a tangled case...
...but if he sticks to Wilmer here...
...he can get a conviction
standing on his head.
Get up on your feet.
I've taken all the riding from you
I'm gonna take.
Get up and shoot it out.
Young Wild West.
Tell him that shooting me
before you get your hands on the falcon...
...is gonna be bad for business.
Now, now, Wilmer. We can't have any
of that.
You shouldn't let yourself attach importance to these things.
-Then tell him to lay off me.
Now, Wilmer.
Your plan is not at all satisfactory, sir.
Let's not say anything more about it.
All right. I've got another suggestion.
It may not be as good as the first,
but it's better than nothing.
-You want to hear it?
-Most assuredly.
Give them Cairo.
Well, by gad, sir.
Suppose we give them you
or Miss O'Shaughnessy? How about that?
You want the falcon. I've got it.
The fall guy's part of the price
I'm asking.
As for Miss O'Shaughnessy, if you think
she can be rigged for the part...
...I'm willing
to discuss it with you.
You seem to forget that you are not
in a position at all to insist upon anything.
Now, come, gentlemen.
Let's keep
our discussion on a friendly basis.
There certainly is something
in what Mr. Cairo said.
If you kill me,
how are you gonna get the bird?
If I know you can't kill me,
how are
you going to scare me into giving it to you?
Sir, there are other means of persuasion
besides killing and threatening to kill.
SPADE:
Yes, that's....
That's true.
But they're none of them any good
unless the threat of death is behind them.
You see what I mean?
If you start something, I'll make it a matter
of your having to kill me,
or call it off.
That's an attitude, sir, that calls for
the most delicate judgment on both sides.
Because, as you know,
in the heat of action...
...men are likely to forget
where their best interests lie...
...and let their emotions
carry them away.
Then the trick from my angle is
to make my play strong enough...
...to tie you up, but not make you
mad enough to bump me off...
-...against your better judgment.
-By gad, sir, you are a character.
Six-two uneven.
They're selling you out, sonny.
I hope you're not letting yourself
be influenced by the guns...
...these pocket-edition desperadoes
are waving around.
Because I've practiced taking guns away
from these boys before...
...so we'll have no trouble there.
-Wilmer here is--
-All right.
Wilmer. Wilmer!
Wilmer!
Wilmer.
There's our fall guy.
Either you'll say yes, or I'll turn the falcon
and the whole lot of you in.
Don't like that, sir.
You won't like it. Well?
You can have him.
I won't be able to get the falcon
till daylight, or maybe later.
It strikes me it'd be best if we did not
get out of each other's sight...
...until our business has been transacted.
You have the envelope?
Miss O'Shaughnessy has it.
Hang on to it.
We don't have to lose sight of each other.
The dingus'll be brought here.
Excellent, sir, excellent.
And in exchange for the 10,000
and Wilmer...
...you'll give us the falcon
and an hour or two of grace.
Let's get the details fixed, first.
Why did he shoot Thursby and why, where
and how did he shoot Captain Jacoby?
I've got to know
all that happened, so I can be sure...
-...the parts that don't fit are covered up.
-I shall be candid with you, sir.
Thursby was Miss O'Shaughnessy's ally.
We believed that disposing of him...
...would cause Miss O'Shaughnessy to stop
and think that it would be best...
...to patch up her differences with us
regarding the falcon.
You didn't try to make a deal
with him before giving him the works?
We did. Yes, sir. We most certainly did.
I talked to him myself that very night,
but I could do nothing with him.
He was quite determinedly loyal
to Miss O'Shaughnessy.
So Wilmer followed him back to the hotel
and did what he did.
That sounds all right.
Now Jacoby.
Captain Jacoby's death was entirely
Miss O'Shaughnessy's fault.
SPADE:
Tell me what happened.
Cairo, as you must have surmised,
got in touch with me...
...after he left police headquarters
yesterday night.
He recognized the mutual advantage
of pooling forces.
Mr. Cairo is a man of nice judgment.
The Paloma was his thought. He saw
the notice of its arrival in the papers...
...and remembered he had heard
in Hong Kong...
...that Jacoby and Miss O'Shaughnessy
were seen together.
Well, sir, he saw that notice and,
putting
two and two together, guessed the truth.
She had given the bird to Jacoby
to bring here for her.
And at that juncture,
you decided to slip me a Mickey?
There was no place for you
in our plan, sir.
So we decided to spare ourselves
any possible embarrassment.
Mr. Cairo and Wilmer and I
went to call on Captain Jacoby.
We were lucky enough to arrive
while Miss O'Shaughnessy was there.
In many ways, the conference was
difficult, but we finally persuaded...
...Miss O'Shaughnessy to come to terms,
or so we thought.
We then left the boat
and set out for my hotel...
...where I was to pay Miss O'Shaughnessy
and receive the bird.
Well, sir, we mere men
should have known better.
En route, she, Captain Jacoby
and the falcon...
...slipped completely through our fingers.
It was neatly done, sir. Indeed, it was.
You touched off the boat before you left?
No, not intentionally.
Though, I daresay, we, or Wilmer at least,
were responsible for the fire.
While the rest of us were talking
in the cabin, Wilmer went about the boat...
...trying to find the falcon.
No doubt, he was careless with matches.
How about the shooting?
We caught up with Miss O'Shaughnessy
and Jacoby at her apartment.
I sent Wilmer downstairs to cover
the fire escape before ringing the bell.
And, sure enough, while she was asking us
who we were through the door...
...and we were telling her,
we heard a window go up.
Wilmer shot Jacoby
as he was coming down the fire escape...
...shot him more than once, but Jacoby
was too tough to fall or drop the falcon.
He climbed down the rest of the way,
knocked Wilmer over and ran off.
We persuaded-- That is the word, sir.
We persuaded Miss O'Shaughnessy...
...to tell us where she had told
Captain Jacoby to take the falcon.
And we further persuaded her
to phone your office...
...in an attempt to draw you away
before Jacoby got there...
...but, unfortunately for us...
...it had taken us too long
to persuade Miss O'Shaughnessy.
And you had the falcon
before we could reach you.
Wilmer, I'm sorry indeed to lose you,
but I want you to know...
...I couldn't be fonder of you
if you were my own son.
But, well, if you lose a son,
it's possible to get another.
There's only one Maltese Falcon.
When you're young,
you simply don't understand these things.
How about some coffee?
Put the pot on, will you, angel?
I don't like to leave our guests.
O'SHAUGHNESSY: Surely.
-Just a moment, my dear.
Hadn't you better
leave the envelope in here?
Sit on it, if you're afraid of losing it.
You misunderstand me.
It's not that at all.
But business should be transacted
in a businesslike manner.
For instance,
there are only nine bills here now.
There were 10 when I handed them to you,
as you very well know.
Well?
I want to know about this.
You palmed it.
-I palmed it?
-Yes.
Do you want to stand for a frisk?
You're going to admit it, or I'm gonna
search you. There's no third way.
I believe you would. I do.
You are
a character, if you don't mind my saying so.
You palmed it.
Yes, sir, that I did.
I must have my little joke now and then.
I was curious to know what
you would do in a situation of this sort.
I must say you passed the test
with flying colors.
It's the sort of thing I'd expect
from somebody Wilmer's age.
This will soon be yours.
You might as well take it.
I ought to have more than 10,000.
You understand
this is the first payment. Later.
Oh, yes. Later you'll give me millions,
but how's about 15,000 now?
Frankly and candidly,
upon my word of honor as a gentleman...
... 10,000 is all the money I can raise.
But you didn't say positively.
Positively.
I'd like to give you a word of advice.
-Go ahead.
-I daresay you're going to give her money...
...but if you don't give her as much
as she thinks she ought to have...
...my word of advice is be careful.
Dangerous?
Very.
-How's the coffee coming, angel?
O'SHAUGHNESSY: In a few minutes.
It's almost daylight, Mr. Spade.
Can you start getting it now?
I guess so.
Hello?
Hello, precious.
I'm sorry to get you up so early.
Now, listen carefully. Here's the plot.
In the holland box at the post office
there's an envelope with my scrawl.
In that envelope, there's a parcel-room
check for the bundle we got yesterday.
Uh-huh.
Now, get that bundle
and bring it here, pdq.
That's a good girl. Now hustle. Goodbye.
Thanks, lady.
Sorry to spoil your day of rest.
Not the first one you've spoiled.
Anything else?
-No. No, thanks.
-Bye-bye, then.
SPADE:
There you are.
Now, after 17 years....
It is it.
But we'll make sure.
Fake.
It's a phony. It's lead.
It's lead.
It's a fake.
You've had your little joke.
Now, tell us about it.
No, Sam. No.
That's the one I got from Kemidov.
I swear it.
You.
It's you who bungled it.
You and your stupid attempt to buy it.
Kemidov found out how valuable it was.
No wonder we had
such an easy time stealing it.
You imbecile.
You bloated idiot.
You stupid fathead, you.
Yes, it's the Russian's hand.
There's no doubt about it.
Well, sir, what do you suggest?
We shed tears
and call each other names...
...or shall we go to Istanbul?
Are you going?
Seventeen years I've wanted that little
item and have been trying to get it.
If we must spend another year
on the quest...
...well, sir, it will be an additional
expenditure in time...
...of only five
and fifteen-seventeenths percent.
I'm going with you.
Wilmer.
[SPADE LAUGHS]
A swell lot of thieves.
GUTMAN: We've little to boast about,
but the world hasn't come to an end...
...just because we've run into a setback.
-I must ask you for that envelope.
-I held up my end. You got your dingus.
It's your hard luck
it wasn't what you wanted.
Now, come, sir, we've all failed...
...and there's no reason for expecting
any of us to bear the whole brunt.
In short, sir,
I must ask you for my 10,000.
This'll take care
of my time and expenses.
Now, sir, we'll say goodbye to you...
...unless you care to undertake
the Istanbul expedition with us.
You don't?
Well, frankly, sir,
I'd like to have you along.
You're a man of nice judgment
and many resources.
Now that there's no alternative...
...I daresay you'll manage
without a fall guy.
-I'll make out all right.
-Well, sir, the shortest farewells are best.
Adieu.
And to you, Miss O'Shaughnessy,
I leave the rara avis on the table there...
...as a little memento.
Hello. Is Sergeant Polhaus there?
Yeah. Put him on. This is Sam Spade.
Hello. Tom? Now, listen.
I've got something for you. Here it is.
Jacoby and Thursby were killed
by a kid named Wilmer Cook.
Yeah. He's about 20 years old, 5'6",
wearing a gray overcoat.
He's working for a man
named Kasper Gutman.
Now, you can't miss Gutman.
He must weigh 300 pounds.
That fellow Cairo's in with him too.
They just left
for the Alexandria Hotel.
You'll have to move fast.
They're blowing town.
Watch yourself when you go up
against the kid.
Yes, that's right. Very.
Now, good luck, Tom.
They'll talk, when they're nailed.
We're sitting on dynamite.
We've only got minutes to get set.
Give me all of it.
When you came to my office,
why did you want Thursby shadowed?
I told you, Sam. I thought he was
betraying me.
You had Thursby hooked.
You wanted
to get rid of him before Jacoby came...
...with the loot so you wouldn't have to
split it with him. Isn't that so?
I thought if he knew someone was following
him
he'd be frightened into going away.
Miles wasn't clumsy enough
to be spotted the first night.
You told Thursby he was being followed.
I told him.
Yes, but please believe me, Sam.
I wouldn't have
if I thought Floyd would kill him.
If you thought he wouldn't kill Miles,
you were right.
Miles hadn't many brains, but he'd had
too many years as a detective...
...to be caught by a man he was shadowing
up a blind alley with his gun on his hip.
But he'd have gone up there
with you, angel.
He was just dumb enough for that.
He'd have looked you up and down, licked
his lips
and gone grinning from ear to ear.
You could have stood
as close to him as you liked...
...and put a hole through him with a gun
you got from Thursby.
-Don't, Sam.
-The police'll be here any minute, now talk.
-Why do you accuse me?
-This isn't the time for that act.
We're both of us sitting under
the gallows.
Now, why did you shoot Miles?
I didn't mean to at first, really, I didn't.
But when I found out
that Floyd couldn't be frightened....
I can't look at you and tell you this, Sam.
You thought Thursby would tackle
Miles and one would go down.
If Thursby was killed,
you were rid of him.
If it was Miles,
you'd see Thursby set up for it.
-Something like that.
-When Thursby wasn't going to...
...you borrowed his gun
and did it yourself.
When you heard Thursby was shot,
you knew Gutman was in town.
You needed somebody
to fill
Thursby's boots, so you came back to me.
Yes. Oh, sweetheart, it wasn't only that.
I'd have come back to you,
sooner or later.
From the very first instant I saw you,
I knew.
Well, if you get a good break,
you'll be out of Tehachapi in 20 years...
...and you can come back to me then.
I hope they don't hang you, precious,
by that sweet neck.
-You're not....
-Yes, angel, I'm gonna send you over.
The chances are you'll get off with life.
That means, if you're a good girl, you'll
be out in 20 years.
I'll be waiting for you.
If they hang you,
I'll always remember you.
Don't, Sam.
Don't say that, even in fun.
I was frightened for a minute.
I really thought....
You do such wild
and unpredictable things.
Now, don't be silly.
You're taking the fall.
You've been playing with me.
Just pretending you cared
to trap me like this.
You didn't care at all.
You don't love me.
I won't play the sap for you.
It's not like that. You can't say that.
You never played square with me
since I've known you.
You know deep in your heart that
in spite of anything I've done, I love you.
I don't care who loves who.
I won't play the sap.
I won't walk in Thursby's and I don't know
how many others' footsteps.
You killed Miles,
and you're going over for it.
How can you do this to me, Sam?
Surely Mr. Archer wasn't
as much to you as....
Listen.
This won't do any good.
You'll never understand me,
but I'll try once and then give it up.
When a man's partner is killed,
he's supposed to do something.
Doesn't make any difference
what you thought of him.
He was your partner, and you're supposed
to do something about it.
And it happens
we're in the detective business.
Well, when one of your organization
gets killed, it's....
It's bad business
to let the killer get away with it.
Bad all around,
bad for every detective everywhere.
You don't expect me to think
these things...
-...are sufficient reason for sending me--
-Wait till I'm through. Then you can talk.
I've no earthly reason to think
I can trust you.
If I do this and get away with it,
you'll have something on me...
...that you can use
whenever you want to.
Since I've got something on you...
...I couldn't be sure that you wouldn't
put a hole in me someday.
All those are on one side.
Maybe some of them are unimportant.
I won't argue about that.
But look at the number of them.
And what have we got on the other side?
All we've got is that maybe you love me
and maybe I love you.
You know whether you love me or not.
Maybe I do. I'll have some rotten nights
after I've sent you over, but that'll pass.
If all I've said doesn't mean anything to you
then forget it and we'll make it just this.
I won't because all of me wants to
regardless of consequences.
You counted on that with me the same
as you counted on that with all the others.
Would you have done this if the falcon
had been real and you'd got your money?
Don't be too sure I'm as crooked
as I'm supposed to be.
That sort of reputation
might be good business...
...bringing high-priced jobs and making it
easier to deal with the enemy...
...but a lot more money would have been
one more item on your side of the scales.
If you'd loved me, you wouldn't have
needed any more on that side.
Come in.
Hello, Tom. Got them?
POLHAUS: Got them.
-Swell.
Here's another one for you.
She killed Miles.
Oh, and I've got some exhibits.
The boys' guns, one of Cairo's...
...and a $1,000 bill I was supposed
to be bribed with.
And this black statuette here
that all the fuss was about.
What's the matter with your playmate?
He looks brokenhearted.
I bet when he heard Gutman's story,
he thought he had me.
Cut it out, Sam.
Well, shall we be getting down
to the hall?
It's heavy.
What is it?
The stuff that dreams are made of.